Hi, welcome to the EEVblog and
Electronics Engineering video blog of
interest to anyone involved in
electronics design. I'm your host, Dave
Jones.
Hi, it's multimeter review time again
and yes, it's another Fluke and it's the
Fluke 117 electrician's multimeter. The
Fluke 117 is the top of the Fluke 110
range of multimeters. It's Fluke's
lowest cost Fluke branded multimeter.
You can get cheaper multimeters made by
Fluke but they're under other brands
like Amprobe. And so this is the
cheapest series available. It's 3-year
warranty and made in China instead of
the lifetime warranty and made in USA
like most of the other high-end Flukes,
the 170 series and the Fluke 80 series
and so on. So I thought we'd take a
quick look at this and see what it's
like being made in China. Is it still as
good as the made in USA Flukes? Well,
let's find out. And you know what we
say,
don't turn it on, take it apart. Okay,
so I've opened it up and check it out.
It's really lovely at first glance. You
just you really get a sense that they've
designed this thing properly. Let's
check it out here. There's a big HRC
fuse. There's a 10 amp current shunt.
The jacks
are separate and they're screwed in like
this. They're soldered in
four places. And two at the back, two at
the front here. It's really nice and
check out these plastic
sort of like a blast shield almost. Not
only does it
not only is it also high voltage
isolation slot but it's like a blast
shield in case the fuse blows or
something like that. And they've got
another one.
They've got another one protecting the
thin the um film resistor network here
and it's just really quite nice. They've
got input overload protection here and
up here and as I've uh said the these
9-V battery contacts soldered straight
onto the board, absolutely brilliant. I
like it. Huge big metal shield here to
protect um all the circuitry. It's just
It's just great. It's really well
designed. This soldering is first class
that you can see and it's just really
what you'd expect out in USA Fluke, but
it's not. This is one of their made in
China ones. So, the quality is really is
just as good.
Okay, I've taken the shield off with uh
just two screws up here. It just lifted
straight off. There's a couple of slots
in there and as you can see there's the
circuitry under there. No surprise, an
MSP430
processor and here this looks like a
little custom uh ASIC device. I'll show
some I'll try and get a close-up photo
of that later, but that's obviously um
that circuitry there is obviously part
of the um
uh non-contact uh voltage alert uh
functionality cuz you can see that
there's it goes off to the shield for
the can and there's two huge caps there
and that's obviously that. So, the um
the uh buzzer's just a standard thing
and here I love this. It's just
terrific. It's a um CD
um 4069,
a 4000 series um hex inverter and you
know, that chip's probably 35, 40 years
old and here it is still used in a
Fluke. I just love that um sort of
generic
uh you know,
uh basic jelly jelly bean logic used in
products like this. The first thing I
noticed about this meter when I picked
it up is that it's it feels beefy and
heavy heavier than you'd expect from its
little uh reasonably compact size. Now,
I'll compare it with the Fluke 87 as a
basic reference, and you can see it's
it's quite it's quite smaller. There's
there's quite a difference there in
these two meters. This one's about 600 g
or thereabouts, and this one's about 400
g, but it feels almost as heavy. It's
really It's really quite nice. And if
you notice, it's it's contoured as well.
It's designed to be held in the hand
like that really really nicely. And it
And it does have this nice sexy curved
feel. Check it out. And the knob around
there is all raised up, and it's
it's it's really quite something to look
at. It's really nice industrial design.
I like it.
And with this knob
being sticking out protruding like this,
has its good points and its bad points,
I think. It's really good in that it's
raised up and you can easily grab a hold
of it and turn, especially if you're
wearing you know, if you're out in the
field and you're wearing gloves or
something like that, as you might do if
you're an electrician, I guess. I'm not
an electrician, but you know, I can
picture they'd use gloves for some
things or something like that. So, it
could be really handy in that respect
that the knob actually sticks out. But
the problem is it does actually stick
out like that. And really, that's I
don't think that's quite as rugged a
design as the recessed switch on the
Fluke 80
series or the Fluke 170 series meters.
And if you drop it, and it lands flat on
its face, it's just going to hit this
knob. And And also, the knob actually
protrudes from the side here as well.
And that's designed for one-hand thumb
operation. And it works really nice. I
like it. But Um, yeah, it's it's
probably not the most rugged solution.
So, they traded off sort of, you know,
ease of ease of handling with
ruggedness, I think. But, still it feels
pretty rugged. I like it.
So, it does feel like a meter that you
can really, uh, just, you know, grab and
throw in your toolbox. Probably not, um,
as as much as the 170 series, but you do
get a lot of confidence that this thing
is going to, you know, really survive
the hard knocks, I think. Now, the
biggest thing about this meter is that
you've got to be aware that it's
designed for electricians. It's not
designed for electronics use. That's why
it only has, uh, the amps,
uh, jack. It's only got a 10 amp 10 20
amp range. It doesn't have milliamps. It
doesn't have microamps, which which
makes it,
you know, almost useless for, uh, more
serious electronics use cuz you've got
to have milliamp or microamp ranges.
But, this is designed for a different
market. So, you know, don't say it's
crap or anything like that because it
doesn't have a milliamp or microamp
range. I know people are going to say
that, but it's, you know, that's why
Fluke make all these different meters
and other manufacturers make all these
different meters. Just like the fuel we
had with the, uh, Agilent meter review
the other week, which went nuts because
people didn't understand that you can
have meters designed for different
things. And this is an electrician's
meter. So, what's the range switch like?
Well, it feels pretty good. It's got the
standard Fluke quality. It's probably
not as sharp as some of the others, but
it's it's got a nice feel to it, nice
sound. It feels pretty rugged and I like
it. And, uh, I don't particularly like
the fact that the off position is here,
so you can't just
you know, bang it all the way back and
turn it off. Uh, it goes into this auto
V, uh,
range, which I'll talk about. But, yeah,
I would have preferred the off to be
right in that position, so you can just
wham it around and it's off. But, you
can't do that. You've got to consciously
go, "Ah, it's now off."
Now, the specs aren't going to set the
world on fire because it's designed for
electrician electrical installation type
use. So, it's 0.5% basic DC volts
accuracy plus two counts.
Very generic. 0.9% plus two counts or
plus one count, I think, for ohms. So,
you know, and don't even ask about the
rest because, well, you know, it's it's
not a super accurate meter and it
doesn't need to be for uh for just
general power electrician use. Other
things that show it's only designed for
electrician use uh really the frequency
range only goes up to 50 kHz, which is
not huge. The well, the frequency
measurement range, it is true RMS, which
is which is good and what you need. Um
but, you know, it doesn't have a huge
bandwidth. And the other thing is is the
cap range on it um has a minimum
resolution of 1 nF, you know, so for
electronics use, 1 nF resolution is
pretty useless.
One thing I do like about it is that uh
the ohms and the continuity are separate
switch positions, so you don't have to
use, you know, they're not uh
multiplexed and use the soft buttons
like the traditional one. So, let's try
out the continuity test response, shall
we?
Absolutely, it's got 500 microsecond
response time. It'll pick up everything.
Excellent. Okay, let's try out the
response of the uh measurement and see
if it see how it goes. When you switch
it on, it it takes a little bit to get
there. It's not the world's fastest
switch, but it doesn't overshoot or
undershoot. So, it's, you know, it's not
too bad at all.
By far the biggest disappointment with
this meter that I found is that, you
know, it's got the hold button there and
you would think that would be the famous
Fluke touch hold, which they've had for,
you know, 20 25 years or something. But,
no, it's one of the cheap crappy hold uh
just manual hold modes that you get on
all the el cheapo 111 m. And oh,
it's like I hate it. It's hopeless.
Look, like you you press it and yeah,
okay, it freezes the uh meter reading,
but
it's you know, you can see the bar graph
change, but it's not
it's not FLUKE TOUCH HOLD. WHY?
BASTARDS. It
tight asses, really. They're just trying
to upsell you to the next meter. Oh.
Okay, let's test out the backlight,
shall we? Here we go.
It's you know, it's quite nice. Look at
it. It's got that uh bluish sort of you
know, it's supposed to be white, but it
ends up being like a blue on the camera
really and a bit blue tinge, but you
know, it's it's quite a nice little even
backlight. Not bad at all.
There's another neat feature of this
which I really like, and that's the low
impedance capacitance measurement mode.
Now, this is real handy for uh noisy uh
capacitance measurements when you're
measuring like the capacitance of a
really long cable in a factory or
something. They can pick up all sorts of
crap and interfere with regular meters,
but this one, if you hold down the range
switch when you turn it on, it's goes
into low cap mode. And you turn it
around to cap and uh
there we go. And it's got low Z low Z uh
cap mode. And I like it.
So, what's the tilting bail like? Well,
it's um it's it's kind of a bit new.
It's once again it's a plastic it's a
sturdy plastic thing. Feels more sturdy
than some other Flukes, but one thing I
really like about it is that it's got
all the power on uh
uh options and features engraved in the
stand. And that's better than what they
did with the Fluke 87 and they just
didn't put it on there at all, even
under the holster. Um they just said
refer to manual, which is stupid. But
they've they've they've learned and
they've put the power on features right
on the back here, and it's good. You can
disable the beeper.
Um you can uh disable auto power off. Um
as I said, you can put it into low
uh impedance capacitance mode.
The other thing you'll notice with the
holster is that it's it's actually a bit
um thinner than uh than the other Fluke
uh holsters. So, if I take it apart
here, you can see it's actually quite
quite a thin
um thin-walled holster, but you know,
it's it's nicely molded to the meter,
and and there's the
there's the contours of the meter. It's
really a nice sexy industrial design. I
really like it, and it does have that
without the uh holster, it's really got
that solid Fluke feel to it. And uh it's
pretty nice. Let's test out the overload
capability of it. Got it hooked up to
the 240-V mains, and uh as you can see,
there we go. Turn it off, and let's go
to this uh auto detect thing they've got
here, which actually automatically
switches between uh AC and DC voltage.
Um but, it's a fixed 600-V range that
one. So, but you know, I I guess it's
going to be handy for some people, but
there you go. Let's switch it to DC.
It's surviving. Let's switch it to
millivolts. Yeah, it's surviving
overload. It's got the high voltage
warning indicator there. Um let's switch
it to ohms. Ohms is of course going to
Oh, it's flashing there, so it's
probably telling you it's you know, it's
doing something stupid.
But, your continuity tester is going to
beep at you. Diode capacitance range is
just chucking a hissy fit. And well, you
know,
it's all survives. Back on 240, as you'd
expect from a Fluke. Let's check out the
auto ranging speed. Here we go.
Well, hang on.
Boom. Yeah, it's pretty quick, as you'd
expect from a from a Fluke. So, not bad
at all.
Now, one thing I think it's lacking in
an electrician's, you know, industrial
type multimeter is input jack warning.
They've only got that on the higher end
Flukes. And once again, they're trying
to save cost or maybe upsell you or
something like that. So, when you
actually switch it in, it tells you it
says lead, make sure you got the lead
plugged in. But, you know, if you've got
it switched to volts and you plug it
into the
amps jack, it doesn't beep at you. So,
you know,
they should have added that for I don't
know how much extra it would have cost,
but it would have been worth it. Now,
I've mentioned this auto
voltage mode here and it switches to 600
volts
AC or DC and it doesn't actually let you
range switch. So, it's fixed on 600
volts. But, what it is is it's low
impedance mode, which means it's about
3K in this case, about 3K input
impedance to reduce the effect of ghost
voltages. And that's that's fairly
important in industrial electrical
applications. And the fact that it's you
can just whack it to that mode and you
don't have to worry about any power on
mode or anything like that. You just
know it's going to work in low impedance
mode. It's quite handy, even though I
don't like the positioning of it. But,
it's still good.
One thing I really like is the battery
compartment for this thing. Under the
tilt stand, there's a single threaded
machine screw there, which you take off
and then this whole back thing just
picks off,
you know, takes off and there's the
integral battery in there held in. Very
nice. I love it. This is a great
industrial design. It's It's just abs-
the usability of this is brilliant. You
don't have to take off the rubber
holster to replace the battery. Sadly,
you can't replace the fuse and you can
see the two terminals soldered directly
onto the board there. And I really love
that. The other thing I like is that the
battery compartment, you can't actually
put the battery in backwards cuz the
terminals, it won't let you physically
push it in. Someone's really thought
about changing the battery on this
thing. I mean, it's got a 400 claimed
400 hour battery life, so you don't have
to change it that often. But, when you
do, it's just it's just brilliant. Okay.
Now, the really deep ribbed walls on
these things and the and the really deep
grooves that they've got around here.
And you might think, "Okay, so what?"
But, that's purposely designed um so
that it it really fits together with
like a a sort of a nice hydraulic feel,
but most importantly to contain um to
make a big air path that well, a very
difficult path for like um you know,
explosions and flames if this thing
somehow meets its demise with an
overload, it doesn't just burst out of
the meter through the seams. And it's
it's really well designed for high
industrial overloads. I like it. One of
the main selling points of this meter is
that well, the top-of-the-line 117 is
that it has uh VoltAlert. It's got it
written on top there and there's an LED
up the top. You switch it right around
to VoltAlert position and it's just like
one of these Fluke uh you know,
non-contact uh voltage alert probes. It
does exactly the same thing. And that's
real handy to have that in a multimeter.
So, you've got one instrument to do, you
know, pretty much everything an
electrician needs. I think it's great.
And the good thing is it's got a high
sensitivity and a low sensitivity mode.
You just press high low there and um
that that determines that the the
distance from the mains wiring that you
can actually measure stuff.
There it is there.
Right next to the thing. And that's on
high range. If you put it on low range,
you've got to get a bit closer than
that.
Um it's I think it's different cuz I'm
actually holding this. If I put it put
it down on the bench here and um you put
it on high range, you can it works about
you know, about that far from the
wiring, you know, a good 4 in, 5 in,
something like that. But the low range,
you've you've pretty much got to get it
within about an inch of like a mains
cable and it seems to work really well.
It's you know, it's not too much
different. It's more sensitive than a
than a standard Fluke
non-contact probe. Okay, let's check the
battery current. I've got it switched
off. I've got it hooked up to my micro
current and it's drawing nothing at all
as you can see. Let's switch it on and
it draws about 1.3 milliamps uh
in just
normal normal
normal operation. 1 milliamp in DC
volts, slightly more in ohms, you know,
it's not a
capacitance mode.
Not a big deal at all. Let's turn the
backlight on.
And 20 milliamps with the backlight on.
So at those sort of currents with a
alkaline 800 milliamp hour battery
roughly, it's it's should easily meet
its 400 hour claimed battery life. No
problems at all. Okay, so I've let the
meter actually switch off and as you can
see it's drawing about 75 microamps in
the sleep mode and that's going to give
you like more than a year of
standby power if you just do that
instead of switch it off. So I'll switch
it off and of course it draws nothing.
Tell us the price, son. Well, it goes
for about a hundred the Fluke 117 is
about 190 US street price really. It's
more than that retail I believe but
that's what you can get it for on the
street. The
the lesser models in the series which
don't have the input voltage alert, the
non-contact voltage alert, they're
cheaper again. I think you can get as
cheap as like a hundred and thirty
dollars or something. But yeah, it's
it's not bad value at all for an
electrician's meter. So the verdict on
the Fluke 117 meter, well, I give it the
thumbs up because it's as an
electrician's meter, only because that's
what it's designed for. If you want it
for electronics, well,
you know, don't even think about buying
it. You know, you wouldn't spend two uh
almost 200 US bucks for one of these
when it doesn't measure milliamp and
microamp. But, you know, if your
applications don't need that, then well,
this is a pretty darn good meter. It's
good value for money, I think. It's uh
it's a three-year warranty made in
China. It's uh you wouldn't know it. Uh
you would think it's it's made in USA.
The um build design and build quality
and component quality is just as good as
any of the other Flukes. I'm quite
surprised, actually. I didn't expect it
to be this um well made for their bottom
of the range meters. But, um well, I
guess for the price, 200 bucks is still
what it's be a well made Fluke. And it
is.
Beauty.